<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Englands patterne and duty in it's monthly fasts presented in a sermon, preached to both Houses of Parliament assembled, on Friday the 21. of July, An. Dom. 1643. : Being an extraordinary day of publicke humiliation appointed by them throughout London and Westminster. that everyone might bitterly bewaile his owne sinnes and cry mightily vnto God for Christ his sake, to remove his wrath, and heale the land / by William Spurstowe sometimes fellow of Katherine Hall in Chambridg [sic], and now pastor of Hackney near London.</title>
            <author>Spurstowe, William, 1605?-1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93722</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5094</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E64_2</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">50290035</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 50290035</idno>
            <idno type="VID">155377</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93722)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 155377)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 11:E64[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Englands patterne and duty in it's monthly fasts presented in a sermon, preached to both Houses of Parliament assembled, on Friday the 21. of July, An. Dom. 1643. : Being an extraordinary day of publicke humiliation appointed by them throughout London and Westminster. that everyone might bitterly bewaile his owne sinnes and cry mightily vnto God for Christ his sake, to remove his wrath, and heale the land / by William Spurstowe sometimes fellow of Katherine Hall in Chambridg [sic], and now pastor of Hackney near London.</title>
                  <author>Spurstowe, William, 1605?-1666.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 31 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Peter Cole at the signe of the Glove in Corne-hill neare the Royall Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Published by Order of both Houses of Parliament."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Samuel, 1st, VII, 6 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:155377:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:155377:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ENGLANDS PATTERNE AND DUTY IN IT'S MONTHLY FASTS <hi>PRESENTED IN</hi> A SERMON, Preached to both Houſes of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> aſſembled, on Friday the 21. of <hi>July, An. Dom.</hi> 1643. BEING An extraordinary Day of publicke Humiliation appointed by them, throughout <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> that every one might bitterly bewaile his owne ſinnes, and crie mightily vnto God for Chriſt his ſake, to remove his wrath, and heale the Land</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> WILLIAM SPURSTOWE <hi>ſometimes Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of</hi> KATHERINE HALL <hi>in Chambridg, and now</hi> Paſtor <hi>of</hi> HACKNEY <hi>near</hi> LONDON.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed by Order of both Houſes of <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>In that day did the Lord God of Hoſts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ll to weeping, and to mourning, and to baldneſſe, and to girding with ſackcloth; and behold joy and gladneſſe, ſlaying oxen, and killing ſheep, eating fleſh, and drinking wine, let vs eate, and drinke for to morrow we ſhall die. And it was revealed in my eares by the Lord of Hoſts; ſurely this iniquity ſhall not be purged from you till you die, ſaith the Lord God of Hoſts,</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>Iſa. 22. 12. 13. 14.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON Printed for <hi>Peter Cole</hi> at the ſigne of the Glove in Corne-hill neare the Royall Exchange, 1643.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:155377:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:155377:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOURABLE The Houſe of Lords AND THE HONOURABLE HOUSE Of Commons <hi>ASSEMBLED IN PARLIAMENT.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is reported of a great <hi>Perſian Monarke,</hi> that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving loſt his royall Conſort, he was ſo deeply affected with ſorrow, as that he refuſed to admit of any comfort: In this height of paſſion, a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Philoſopher</hi> vndertooke, if that he would fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh him with things neceſſarie for his purpoſe, to raiſe the <hi>dead Queen</hi> againe: the <hi>Empirour</hi> much taken with the <hi>offer,</hi> was willing for that end, to exhauſt all his <hi>Treaſures:</hi> but the other only demanded of him three names of ſuch perſons as had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver felt any greife or ſadneſſe, to engrave them on the <hi>Queens</hi> Monument: which after much ſearch throughout his <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire</hi> could not be found. I to the reſtoring of this bleeding &amp; dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Kingdom,</hi> whoſe wounds every day grow wider and wider, ſhall not deſire the names of any ſuch perſons as have been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together ſtrangers vnto ſorrow and humiliation, they being thoſe that have drawne the heavieſt judgments vpon it; but the names of ſuch as have been reall and ſolemne mourners before God in the behalfe of this <hi>Land,</hi> which if in any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent number they may be found, I ſhall not feare but this <hi>Kingdome</hi> may ſee a glorious and happy <hi>reſurrection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This affection of ſorrow is that which this <hi>Sermon</hi> did firſt call for, from the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> and doth ſtill continue (being pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by your Command) to doe it from the <hi>Preſſe,</hi> as being the moſt ſutable poſture and dreſſe to the preſent conditon of this <hi>Land,</hi> it cals and invites all, to an holy mourning
<pb facs="tcp:155377:3"/> and humiliatiation before the Lord, whoſe ſinnes have bin as oyle to the lampe, and fuell vnto the fire, to feed and nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh that diſpleaſure, that burnes in the bowels of the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> But more eſpecially your <hi>Honours,</hi> who are the <hi>two eyes</hi> of the <hi>Kingdome</hi> not only to watch over it for it's good, but to mourne over it for it's ſinnes and miſerie: not only to be <hi>Reformers</hi> of it, but <hi>Weepers</hi> for it. And the <hi>firſt ſtones</hi> of <hi>Reformation,</hi> which are not like the <hi>foundation</hi> of the <hi>Temple,</hi> that was laid with the <hi>weepings</hi> of the old men, and the <hi>ſhout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi> of the young men, but with the bitter mourning of all ſorts will (I doubt not) in the finiſhing, and perfecting of the worke receive the joyfull acclamations both of young and old, both of <hi>Governours</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> the God of Heaven him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe turning our water into wine on the wet <hi>ſeed-time</hi> of <hi>teares,</hi> into an <hi>harveſt</hi> of <hi>joy</hi> and ſpirituall bleſſings: which that he may ſpeedily doe, prayes,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours to ſerve you for Chriſt. WILLIAM SPURSTOWE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:155377:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREACHED To both Houſes of PARLIAMENT On Friday, the 21. of <hi>July,</hi> 1643.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>1. Sam. 7. 6.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And they gathered together to Mizpeh, and drew water, and powred it out before the Lord, and faſted that day, and ſaid there, we have ſinned againſt the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſtrength and happineſſe of the State and Kingdome of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> was (if you looke into the preſent Story) ſorely ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and waſted from a double Hand, the Sword of God, and the Sword of Man: the Sword of the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> in one Battell tooke away thirtie thouſand, and the Sword of God at one ſtroake ſwept away fifty thouſand. <note place="margin">Cap. 4. 10. Cap. 6. 19.</note> So that all <hi>Iſrael</hi> in this ſad plight wherein they ſtand, can ſcarce tell what elſe is left them for to doe, but to bewaile
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:155377:4"/> their condition: The <hi>Philiſtines</hi> they are ſtrong and cannot be reſiſted, God is angerie, and will not be intreated; they ſigh unto him through the weight of their oppreſſions, but are not eaſed, they <hi>lament after him,</hi> but doe not find him.</p>
            <p>In this exigency, the Prophet <hi>Samuel</hi> counſels and excites <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to the practice of two moſt ſeaſonable duties, to a <hi>reall and perfect Reformation,</hi> v. 3. to a <hi>deep and ſerious Humiliation, ver. the fift,</hi> the joynt performance of both which, procure no leſſe then a miraculous helpe from Heaven, to the ruine of the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> and ſalvation of all <hi>Iſraell ver.</hi> 10. 11.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Text</hi> (which I have read) containes the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi> and <hi>Manner</hi> of <hi>Iſraels</hi> performance of that ſecond duty, to which the <hi>Prophet</hi> did excite them: And in it there are theſe two partes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The parts of the Text.</note> Firſt, a <hi>generall Convention and meeting</hi> of the whole State and Kingdome. <hi>They ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hered together to Miſpeh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, a <hi>particular account</hi> of what they did at this Meeting, and that is ſet downe in three Actions: 1. they <hi>drew water, and poured it out before the Lord,</hi> 2. <hi>And faſted on that day,</hi> 3. <hi>And ſaid there, we have ſinned before the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe three Actions (inlightning the firſt only with ſome breife <hi>Commentarie)</hi> will exactly poynt out the duty and taſke of this Day, which is a Day of <hi>mourning,</hi> a Day of <hi>faſting,</hi> and a Day of <hi>ſelfe arrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning before the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And drew water and poured it out before the Lord.</hi> Some <hi>Interpreters</hi> vnderſtand it of the water of <hi>Purification,</hi> whereby they teſtified their hope and faith in the remiſſion and waſhing away of their ſinnes. Others thinke that their drawing and pouring forth of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, was a lively ceremony to expreſſe the great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:155377:4"/> of their Humiliation, that their Soules were poured forth as water upon the ground. <note place="margin">Hieroin <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Quaeſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit Hebr.</note> 
               <hi>Hierome</hi> goes alone, at leaſt without any conſiderable Traine, and ſaith, that into this water Curſes were throwne; and that as in the Law, the water of Jelouſie was appoynted for the triall of Adulterie, ſo was this for the tryall of Idolatours whoſe lips did clamme and cleave together, when they had taſted of it.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Chaldee,</hi> whom <hi>Junius</hi> and <hi>Oſiander</hi> follow, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound it of the plentie of teares, which ſtreamed from their eyes as ſo many fountaines. And this laſt ſenſe, ſhall I at preſent cloſe with: and ſo turne the three Actions in <hi>Iſraels Nationall Convention</hi> (in the middeſt of which faſting is ſo ranked, as to eye and reſpect both the other) into two poynts ſutable to this <hi>repreſentative Aſſembly</hi> of this whole Kingdome now met about the ſame worke and duty.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>that true faſters ſhould be weepers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>that in faſting there ſhould be an acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment and confeſſion of ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Doct. 1.</note> That <hi>true faſters ſhould be weepers.</hi> Faſting and teares you ſhall find in Scripture to be like two twines that cannot be ſeperated, like a paire of mournfull Doves that alwayes accompany together, <hi>Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi> 1. 4. <hi>I ſat down and wept, and mourned certaine dayes, and faſted and prayed before the God of Heaven.</hi> Joel 2. 12. <hi>Turne yee to me with all your heart, and with faſting, and with weeping, and with mourning. Heſter</hi> 4. 3. <hi>And eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Province whether-ſoever the Kings Commandement and his Decree came, there was great mourning among the Jewes and faſting, and weeping, and wailing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the cleare explicating of this poynt; I will propound two thinges.</p>
            <p>Firſt I will ſhew, why teares are requiſite to faſting.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:155377:5"/>
            <p>Secondly, what qualifications thoſe teares ſhould have, which are ſhed in a day of Faſt and Humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Teares are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite to faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for 3. reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects.</note> Firſt, why teares are requiſite to faſting, and that in theſe three reſpects.</p>
            <p>Firſt, in regard of the prevalencie that teares have with the God of Mercy and bowells. <hi>Euſebius</hi> tels a Storie of a certaine <hi>Altar</hi> that was <hi>Clementiae conſecrata, dedicated and conſecrated to mercy,</hi> upon which no other Sacrifice was to be layed but teares; intimating therby, a peculiar aptnes in tears to ſtirre up bowels, and to beget Compaſſions, above all other Sacrifices whatſoever: And indeed with God we ſhall find them of that e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>cacy, as that none have bedewed his <hi>Altar</hi> with their unfeined teares, but he hath made their Faces to ſhine with his oyle of gladneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hannah in bitterneſſe of Soule, prayed vnto the Lord, and wept ſore:</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 1. 10. <hi>But ſhe went her way, and her countenance was no more ſad: ver.</hi> 18. Good <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chia,</hi> by his prayer and teares, reverſed the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of death; and had fifteen yeares added vnto his dayes, 2. <hi>King.</hi> 20. 5. 6. <hi>Jacob had power with God: yea, he had power over the Angel, and prevailed:</hi> but how? <hi>he wept and made ſupplication vnto him, Hoſea</hi> 12. 3. 4.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prevalency of teares ſtrang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, in 2. reſpects.</note> And this prevalency of teares, as it is great, ſo it is ſtrange and wonderfull, and that in a double re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Deorſum fluunt, et Coelum petunt:</hi> They drop and fall from the eyes to the earth, but yet by their power they reach and pearce the higheſt Heavens.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Mutae ſunt, et loquntur:</hi> They hold their peace, and yet they crie, they are mute, and yet they ſpeak, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6. 8. <hi>The Lord hath heard the voyce of my weeping, Lam.</hi> 2. 18. In the Originall it runes thus, <hi>Non taceat
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:155377:5"/> pupilla oculi tui,</hi> let not thine eye hold its peace.</p>
            <p>A ſecond reſpect, that makes teares requiſite, is, becauſe the eye hath been the <hi>cheifeſt Broker</hi> for ſin and vanitie: Sinne made its firſt enterance by the eye, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 6. and ſtill it is one of the wideſt Gates by which luſts and follies are let into the Soule.</p>
            <p>Fit therefore it is, that in the duties of humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the eye ſhould beare a part with the other members of the body; that as the heart doth ſigh, the face doth bluſh, the tongue doth crie, the hand knockes the breaſt, the lippes doe tremble, and the knees do bend, ſo the eye ſhould mourne and weep, it having exceeded in guilt any other part, and member of the body; otherwiſe it's rather the eye of an Idol, then of a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Three things occaſion tearce.</note> A third reſpect, is taken from the confluence of all thoſe thinges in a day of Humiliation, which vſually are the occaſions, and riſe of teares.</p>
            <p>Now, there are three things, that doe diſpoſe and incline a perſon to weeping.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The loſſe, or abſence of ſome Great Good: That was it which put <hi>Micha,</hi> Judges 18. 24. into ſuch a ſtrange mixture of paſſions, of anger, weeping, crying out, when being asked, <hi>what aileth him?</hi> he replies, <hi>ye have taken away my gods which I made and the preiſt, and ye are gone away: and what have I more? and what is this that you ſay unto me what aileth thee?</hi> that was it which ſprang as a new leake in <hi>Maries</hi> eys <hi>Joh.</hi> 20. 13. <hi>They have taken away my Lord, and I know not where they have layd him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> that was it which made <hi>David</hi> and his people when <hi>Ziklag</hi> was burnt with fire, and their wives, their ſonns, and their daughters were taken captives, <hi>to lift up their voyce and weepe, untill they had no
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:155377:6"/> more power to weep,</hi> 1. Sam. 30. 4. Now in a day of faſting what truly broken and humbled heart reflecting up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on its owne condition, finds not ſuch a loſſe of peace with God, ſuch ſuſpenſions of light from God, ſuch an abſence of holyneſſe in it ſelfe, ſuch a want of mortification of luſtes, as may juſtly call for teares, ſighes, and what ever elſe doth vſually attend great ſorrow? But eſpecially we on this day have cauſe to mourne, having loſſe upon loſſes, that may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voake us thereunto: A loſſe of Worthies, that have lately fallen, and miſcaried in our <hi>Iſraell,</hi> a loſſe of hopes and affaires in State, a loſſe of expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in maine bleſſinges, that concerne the beautie and the ſettlement of the Church whoſe Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are ſtill ſhaken by the violence and oppoſition of many ſonnes of <hi>Belial,</hi> that are riſen up againſt it. In a word, I am affraid, that moſt of us are this day at a loſſe in regard of all thoſe affections, of feare, of ſhame, of indignation, which ſhould be a ſtirring in this preſent duty; the very want of which may cauſe us to weepe, in that we can faſt and mourne no better before the Lord.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>the feare of ſome great approaching evill.</hi> In the <hi>Object</hi> which moves, and begets feare, <hi>futurition</hi> is required as a neceſſarie condition; but yet all evill the leſſe <hi>future</hi> it is, the more <hi>dreadfull</hi> it is: it being with the <hi>Objects</hi> of paſſion in neareneſſe of time, as it is with the <hi>Objects</hi> of ſence in neareneſſe of place; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinquitie in either making the objects more preſent, and the impreſſions therefrom upon the faculties more ſtrong. The feare of <hi>Ninivehes</hi> ſpeedy deſtruction (which was prophecied to be within foutie dayes) did ſtrike that Heathen King with ſuch apprehenſions of dread, as to make him change his Throne for the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:155377:6"/> pavement, his roabes for ſackecloath, his mirth and fulneſſe into a bitter mourning and faſting. <hi>Jonah</hi> 3. 6. the going out of the Decree of <hi>Ahaſuerus,</hi> to deſtroy and extirpate forthwith all the Jewes, was that which filled everie Dwelling with ſadneſſe, and everie eye with teares. <hi>In everie province whetherſoever the Kings Commandement and his Decree came, there was great mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning among the Jewes, and faſting, and weeping, and wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. Eſt.</hi> 4. 3.</p>
            <p>Now, if the feare of imminent evills doe occaſion weeping, what wonder is it if a <hi>faſter</hi> be a <hi>weeper?</hi> who feares almoſt everie evill to be feared: He feares that God may call to rememberance his former iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and make him to poſſeſſe the ſinnes of his youth, and therefore weeps: <note place="margin">Pſal. 79. 8. Iob. 13. 26.</note> He feares that God, <hi>whoſe blowes he can better brooke then his abſence,</hi> will not be intreated to take vp in his boſome, but hold him as a ſtranger, and therefore weepes: He feares, that his ſinnes, his deafeneſſe to Gods call, his conterluſtings to Gods will, his impuritie in Gods ſervice, his ſecuritie vnder Gods Judgments may cauſe the hand of Heaven, which is lifted vp in threatnigs, to fall downe in ſeveare pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, and therefore weepes. Speake you, whoſe hearts and eyes are exerciſed in this dayes du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, are not theſe and ſuch-like evills the cauſes of your feares, and the motives to your weeping?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>the ſence and ſmart of ſome greivous paine and extremitie.</hi> That is it, which in Hell cauſes an eternall weeping and gnaſhing of teeth, the fire alwayes burnes, the worme continually gnawes, they have no moment free from paine, therefore no moment free from teares. Now this cauſe of mourning meets with both the former in a day of humiliation as lines in a Center, to make <hi>faſters</hi> to become <hi>weepers;</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:155377:7"/> for then it is, that the afflicted ſoule is made ſicke with ſinne, and burthened with the weight of its owne guilt, cries out, who will take this dagger out of my bowells, this poyſoned arrow out of my heart, this milſtone off my backe, this fire out of my bones, theſe ſtinges out of my conſcience? then it is, that ſeeming ſweetneſſe of ſin is turned into gall, and the heart of a ſinner is ſcalded with the eſtuations of thoſe luſts, with which formerly it pleaſed it ſelfe: not vnlike to the fiſh that is often times boyled in that water in which it ſwimes and ſportes it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>I now come to the ſecond particular propounded, to ſhew what kind of teares ſhould be ſhed in Faſts. For there are <hi>lacrymae mentiri doctae</hi> (as <hi>Bernard</hi> ſpeakes) <note place="margin">Ber. Ep. 247.</note> teares that are taught to lye and feigne. There are <hi>praeficarum lachrymae,</hi> the teares of hired women, which gaine and monie drawes from them, <hi>Jer.</hi> 9. 17. there are <hi>lachrimae Hiericuntinae,</hi> teares that are like <hi>Jerichoes</hi> waters, though the duties are ſweet in which they be ſhed, yet they are bitter and vnpleaſing.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Six properties of prevailing teares.</note> I ſhall therefore acquaint you with ſix properties, that teares that will preavaile ought to have.</p>
            <p>Firſt: <hi>They muſt ſpring from a tender and broaken heart freely and voluntarily:</hi> They muſt be like water from a <hi>living fountaine</hi> that flowes naturally; not like wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from a <hi>dead pitt</hi> that is drawne forth with en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines: like water from a <hi>cloud,</hi> that is melted by the Sun; not like water from a <hi>Still</hi> that is forced with fire: the beames of Gods love are they which muſt di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>olve our hearts, and not the fire of his judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. An hard heart in times of ſore diſtreſſe may have plentie of teares, and yet retaine its hardneſſe; like marble that ſweates in foule weather, but is not the ſofter: An <hi>Ahab</hi> may humble himſelfe when <hi>God</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:155377:7"/> threatens, and a <hi>Felix</hi> may tremble when he heares of Judgment: <note place="margin">2. King. 23. 29. Act 24. 25.</note> But a <hi>Joſiah</hi> only whoſe teares ſpring from a broken and tender heart, ſo mournes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to pleaſe God, and prevaile with God: <hi>Chron.</hi> 2. 34. 27. <hi>Becauſe thine heart was tender and thou didſt humble thy ſelfe before God, and didſt rend thy clothes, and weepe before me, I have even heard thee alſo ſaith the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 3. 6.</note> Secondly, <hi>Prevailing teares, muſt be reforming, and clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing teares,</hi> not ſuch as wet only the face, but ſuch as <hi>waſh</hi> the heart. Humiliation without reformation, is like the Word of God in the Letter, which <hi>kils,</hi> and not <hi>quickens,</hi> which <hi>accents</hi> ſinne, &amp; not <hi>leſſens</hi> it, which <hi>haſtens</hi> judgement, and not <hi>defers</hi> it. <hi>Paleneſſe</hi> in the face, and <hi>blood</hi> in the heart, <hi>whiteneſſe</hi> in the eye, and <hi>blackneſſe</hi> in the ſoule, a knee-bowing to him, and <hi>thoughts</hi> riſing up againſt him, an <hi>head</hi> hanging downe like a bull-ruſh, and an <hi>heart</hi> like an Adamant hard and unreformed, are of all ſinnes in Gods ſight the worſt: like the Leaproſie in the Law, which was ever uncleaneſt when whiteſt: And ſhall by God be doomed with the heavieſt of judgements. Hyprocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie is the firſt borne of Hell, and muſt there looke for its double portion: Oh therefore take heed to your ſelves what you doe this day! be ſure you that are <hi>faſters</hi> be <hi>reformers,</hi> bring your lives to the Rule, and your actions to the Law of God, and let all run para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lell with the Word, as an exact, and well-made Diall with the Sunne.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Prevailing teares and ſorrow muſt eye that more, which diſhonoureth God, then that which afflictes our ſelves:</hi> they muſt be more for that which fighteth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his <hi>Image,</hi> then for what is contrary to our <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture:</hi> more for that which defileth the <hi>ſpirit,</hi> then for that which paineth the <hi>fleſh:</hi> we muſt grieve more
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:155377:8"/> that ſinne hath made us <hi>unholy,</hi> then that it hath made us unhappy, that wee have run out of the way of the Law, then that we have run in danger of the Law: wee muſt not cry onely with <hi>Pharoah,</hi> take away this <hi>plague:</hi> but with <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the Prophet, take away all <hi>Iniquity,</hi> and receive us graciouſly, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14. 2.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Briſſon de Reg. Perſi. lib. 2.</note> Fourthly, <hi>Prevailing teares muſt be conſtant.</hi> The <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians</hi> had one day in a yeare a feſtivall, which they called <hi>vitiorum interitum,</hi> wherein they ſlew all Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents, and venemous creatures, and after that till the returne of the ſame day, ſuffered them to ſwarme as faſt as ever: not in an unlike manner doe many mourne for their ſins; at ſome ſet day in the moneth, or the yeare appointed by the State, they hang down their head, they cry out of their ſinnes, and make pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsions of better living, and then till the revolution of the ſame time, ſuffer them to ſpread in their lives, and to grow up in their converſations as faſt as ever.</p>
            <p>But thoſe ſuddain motions and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>aſhes, thoſe <hi>fits,</hi> and ſtarts in humiliation, are ſo far wide from the mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of a true Chriſtian, who in a conſtant and regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar courſe crucifies his luſts, weakens the ſtrength of ſin, ſighs over his corruptions when he cannot weepe and has a <hi>bleeding heart</hi> oft times, when not a <hi>wet eye;</hi> as that they will be never able to denominate that man a Chriſtian in whome they are only found. <note place="margin">In Categ. cap. de qualit.</note> 
               <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> excellently diſtinguiſheth between <hi>colours</hi> that ariſe from paſſion, and from <hi>complection.</hi> The one he ſaith giveth the <hi>denomination</hi> to the ſubject wherein it is, which the other doth not. If the Queſtion be asked, what a like man is <hi>Socrates?</hi> If he be of a pale or high-coloured <hi>complection,</hi> it may be fitly Anſwered, that he is a <hi>pale</hi> man, or a <hi>ſanguine</hi> man; but when a man of another complection
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:155377:8"/> is <hi>pale</hi> for feare, or <hi>red</hi> with <hi>bluſhing;</hi> we doe not vſe to ſay, neither can we properly, that he is a <hi>pale</hi> man, or an <hi>high-coloured.</hi> Accordingly in matters of grace, and duties of holyneſſe: we cannot ſay he is a <hi>penitent,</hi> a <hi>zelous,</hi> a <hi>religious</hi> man, whoſe conſtant motions are in a way of ſinne, and his <hi>humiliations</hi> only in ſome ſhort <hi>fits,</hi> that are ſcarce ſo long as the <hi>paroxciſme</hi> of a burning Ague, which in a few howers goes off againe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fiftly, prevailing teares muſt drop from the eye of hope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To mourne and not to hope, hath a double evill in it, both in that it defiles, and in that it ruines a man: <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>files,</hi> in that it conceives low and baſe thoughts of God himſelf: in rendering our guilt more omnipotent then his power, and ſin more hurtful then he is good: <hi>ruines,</hi> in that the mind is thereby driven to a dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full flight, and wretched contempt of all the true meanes of recoverie. But hope which is as the corke to the net, that keeps it floating amid'ſt the rougheſt Seas, teacheth a relapſed yet repenting ſinner, when he deſpaires in himſelfe to fly to God, when he ſees nothing below him, nothing about him, to beleive there is ſomething above him that can, and will ſupport: It quickens him alſo in the vſe of everie meanes, and makes him to doe as <hi>Marie did,</hi> who being above other ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull for the loſſe of Chriſt, was above all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther moſt dilligent to ſeeke him.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, <hi>prevailing teares muſt be timely and ſeaſonable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hiſtorians make mention of a fountaine that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſent out any ſtreams, but the evening before a famine: this fountaine (I am afraid) our teares have too much reſembled, which have been ſo
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:155377:9"/> late as to ſerve only to bemoane our miſerie, and not to prevent it: had we wept more timely (I am perſwaded) wee ſhould not have ſo many oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ons of weeping, as we now have: we now weep, becauſe the meanes of our hope are much blaſted, and ſucceſſe denyed to our enterpriſes, but we ſhould have wept vnto God that they might have bin bleſſed, and proſpered by his favour. We mourne now becauſe the Heavens are darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with Gods diſpleaſure, which is ready to fall in ſtormes vpon us, but we ſhould have mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned when the cloud was but an hands breadth, and ſo prevented the gathering of it: and yet let me not diſcourage any, that are newly entered vpon this duty of mourning, as if it were altogether too late: the Jewes had a ſaying amongſt them, that the dore of prayer hath ſometimes bin ſhut, but never the dore of teares, and therefore, you that have not yet mourned, now beginne, and you that have begun, ſtill continue, for <hi>who knoweth, if God will returne, and repent, and leave a bleſſing behind him, Ioel</hi> 2. 14.</p>
            <p>I now haſten to application: wherein,</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. Vſe.</note> Firſt, I ſhall endeavour to provoke all to an holy, and exceptable weeping, before the Lord.</p>
            <p>It is the errand we all come about, let vs not therefore goe away, and leave it vndone. Oh that this day you Nobles and Rulers of the people would begin to them in this weighty ſervice, the mourning of a Great Perſon is moſt powerfull Rhetoricke to perſwade others to weepe:
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:155377:9"/> as running metall, will ſooner melt other of it's owne kind then fire alone: ſo will examples ſooner frame mens minds to the ſame temper, then bare and naked devotions can ever doe: neither is it any minoration of your Greatneſſe, to weepe, and to be humbled before your God, to licke the duſt of whoſe feet is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Honour, then to poſſeſſe Crownes and Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, without his Favour: Oh that I could pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile with you of the People, to make this place a <hi>Bochim</hi> with your tears! and to this end I could wiſh, that I had ſome <hi>Moſes</hi> his Rod in my hand, to ſmite all the Rockes that are before me, that they might flow forth with water: A Rod (I meane) of perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that might diſſolve, and melt your hearts into teares: I had thought to framed many, and to have told you, that they are <hi>Theriaca poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſima,</hi> the beſt Triacle to expell the venome of ſinne, <hi>lixivium forte,</hi> the ſtrongeſt ly to waſh out the deepeſt ſtaines; <hi>imbres vere aurei,</hi> the true golden ſhowers, in which God comes downe into the heart of a Chriſtian. But that we may looſe no time in the dutie, give me leave to, propound Five melting Conſiderations, that may incline you to a ſerious mourning.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Five melting Conſiderations.</note> Firſt, <hi>take into your thoughs your condition by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi> And ſuch a one it is, which teares and ſighes may better expreſſe then words: a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of nakedneſſe, blood, impotencie, wrath, (in one word) of ſinne. Hell it ſelfe, which is the draine and ſole receptacle of ſin, and ſinners, is not more full of ſinne in regard of the kinds of it, then your Natures: For, the Seedes
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:155377:10"/> of all thoſe ſinnes, for which the damned are now tormented in hell, lye hid in our hearts, all being alike corrupted in the roote; and therefore it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoves you, if you would eſcape the fulneſſe of wrath, which is due to the fulneſſe of ſinne that is in you, to crie mightily unto God that he would pitty you, yea though your natures be changed, yet you have cauſe ſtill to weepe and mourne. For as <hi>Baſil</hi> ſaid of the roſe, that it was a faire flower, but it wanted not his prickles, that might put him in mind of the curſe the earth was ſubject vnto; ſo in the beſt, there are thoſe remainders and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques of ſinne, which may cauſe them to mourne and weepe ſtill before the Lord.</p>
            <p>Secondly, let me propound <hi>the preſent occaſion as an inducement vnto weeping.</hi> Did you not take this day to afflict your ſoules before God, as not knowing whether you might ſee any more the returne of your monthly Faſts, ſo exceedingly did the wrath of God haſten it's progreſſe againſt you? And now, when you come vnto the dutie, will you doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, that may witneſſe how bitter your ſinnes are unto you, that have procured all thoſe evils? Let me tell you, and that without prophecying, if that which God hath already done, prevaile not to humiliation, that there are judgments not far off, that will prevaile to ruine and deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, conſider, <hi>what a ſhame it is for a chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, that croſſes and feares ſhould ſit heavie, and that ſinne ſhould ſit light on his ſpirits.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sometimes the ſmart of a ſingle croſſe enters ſo deep into vs, as that all expreſſions of ſorrow ſeem to be far below what we feel: Sometimes, the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie newes of an approaching danger, fils the eye
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:155377:10"/> with tears, and the mouth with ſhreeks: And yet when we come to ſtand at Gods Bar (as we all doe this day) the confeſſions of the rebellion of our whole lives, the ſad Hiſtorie our finnes, and the acknowledgment of Gods wrath due to all, make ſuch weake impreſſions vpon our ſpirits, as they ſcarce produce a ſigh or troubled thought about our condition: Now what a ſhame is it, to heare more outcries from a Chriſtian for one croſſe then for thouſand ſinnes, one of which, hath in it more power and venome to afflict the conſcience, and to make life miſerable, then many legions of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>Conſider, the Lord Chriſt himſelfe how deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he was affected when he ſtood vnder the weight of our ſinnes, and his Fathers wrath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>St <hi>Luke</hi> ſpeakes much in one word, when he tels vs, that Chriſt was in an <hi>agonie, Luke</hi> 22. 44, but if you pleaſe to admit a breife Commentarie vpon it, out of the <hi>Evangeliſts</hi> themſelves, you may then learne, how ſharpe and bitter the <hi>ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie</hi> was. <note place="margin">Mar. 14. 33: Mat. 26. 37. 38.</note> Will you ſee how it affected his Head? vpon the fore-taſte he began <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>to be amazed;</hi> how it affected his heart? he began <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>to droope, to faint;</hi> how it affected his ſoule? <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, it was all overcaſt with a heavineſſe to death; how it affected his body? it made it <hi>to ſweate great drops of blood. Luke</hi> 22. 44. Shall now our ſinnes thus affect Chriſt and not afflict vs? ſhall they be as monntaines upon his backe, and as Attomes on ours? like to the ſtone of the <hi>Sybils, (Dio. Chry. orat.</hi> 13.) which to ſome weighed like leade, and others like a feather: If ſo, know for a certaine, that you whoſe hearts the love of a bleeding
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:155377:11"/> and crucified Saviour doe not melt, his glorious and terrible power ſhall one day break and afflict for ever.</p>
            <p>Fiſtly, Conſider, <hi>we have all contributed to that mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplicitie of evils vnder which the Kingdome labours and ſtrugles for life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Had Great ones bin more reſolute for God, and not like the top of a Fiſhers Angling rod, have bowed and bended to all purpoſes, and indang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger <hi>Religion</hi> to ſave their <hi>Honours,</hi> had our Magiſtrates bin more wakefull to prevent both the ſowing and growth of divers tares, had our Miniſters bin more conſcientious, then to daub with vntempered mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and to expoſe glaſſe for pearles, <note place="margin">Tertul.</note> had all of vs leſſe complyed with vanities, with faſhions, and ſinnes of the time, God had not been ſo angerie, nor we ſo miſerable, as now we are. Requiſite therefore it is, that as we have brought feuell to the fire to nouriſh it, ſo we now bring water, to quench it, and not ſtand, as many doe, when an houſe is on fire, like idle ſpectatours, that hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der rather then further the quenching.</p>
            <p>I have done this vſe, and only by way of cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall adde a few words to releive ſome troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſouls, with whom <hi>tears</hi> perhaps are ſcarce, though <hi>grenes</hi> are plentifull: be not diſcouraged, as if you had done nothing in the dutie of the day, you have had a rationall ſorrow, though not a paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate ſorrow, you have had ſighes which are the inward tears, (as <hi>Auſtin</hi> cals them) though not the outward; and that is the mourning which is moſt effectuall with God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. Vſe.</note> To diſcover (for happily we may wonder) why our humiliations and faſtings which have bin ſo
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:155377:11"/> frequent, have not bin returned with ſucceſſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our boſomes, ſutable to our deſires: but that ſtill there are as many dangerous ſymptomes of a lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing and dying Kingdome as ever. We have Faſted, but have we wept? we have wept, but have we wept aright? Give me leave to run o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver three of thoſe foremention'd qualifications, and you ſhall ſee eminent defects in our weepings.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Three defects in our weeping.</note> Firſt, the teares which have been ſhed, have bin rather forced then voluntarie, more from the ſmart of Stroakes, then the ſence of ſin, more from a want of outward contentments, then for the loſſe of Gods favour: And therefore it is no wonder, if we ſay with Iſrael we have cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>the Altar of the Lord with teares, with weeping, and with crying out,</hi> and yet he regardeth it not, <hi>Mal.</hi> 2. 13.</p>
            <p>Secondly, our teares have not been reforming teares. And here give me leave (Right Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable) to ſpeake to you whom Reformation moſt concerns, you have paſſed worthy Votes for a ſtrict Obſervation of the Sabbath and of faſting dayes, but you have been too apt to ſit downe without a purſuance of the ſame. Alas! it is not a naked Vote that paſſeth within your walls, that can vote our Churches full and the Taverns emptie: there muſt ſomething elſe be done, before a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation in either will be obtained; offenders muſt be puniſhed, Miniſters of Juſtice muſt he quickened, and called vpon by your ſelves: for elſe you will find that true which <hi>Alphius</hi> the vſurer ſometime ſaid of his clients, <hi>Optima nomina non appellando fiere mala: (Colum. de re ruſt. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 7.) good Debters will grow bad paymaſters; if they be let alone.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:155377:12"/>
            <p>Thirdly, our mourning have not been conſtant. The hearing of ſome ill tydings, the miſcarying of ſome hopes have cauſed vs to hang downe our heads for a day, and to power forth ſome teares in the preſence of God: but when theſe things have bin a little digeſted and ſlept vpon, we have bin as ſecure about our conditions, dead and flat in our duties as ever before. Our tears have bin like wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the conduits, that runnes at times; but not like water in the ſpring that rnnes conſtantly: by fits and ſtarts we have bin earneſt with God, like the graſſe-hoppers (as <hi>Gregorie</hi> ſpeakes) <note place="margin">Greg. mor. lib. 13. cap. 12.</note> that make faint aſſaies to fly vp to Heaven, and then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently fall to the earth againe. But if ever wee would appeaſe God, while his anger burnes, let our eye weep; while he denies, let us beg; while he withdrawes and abſents himſelfe, let vs vnceſſantly crie out, as the Church did, <hi>Jer.</hi> 14. 9. <hi>Oh thou hope of Jſrael, the Saviour therof in the time of trouble, why ſhouldeſt thou be as a ſtranger in the Land, and as a way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faring man that turneth a ſide to tarry for a night.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I come now to the ſecond poynt, which is,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That with faſting and weeping Confeſſion and acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſinne is to be joyned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The vſing of certaine words in healing the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes of the body, with which many ignorant people are better acquainted then with prayer, is no other then a ſinfull Charme, but in curing the diſeaſes of the ſoule, and diverting the Judgments of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven words are Gods <hi>Recipe: Hoſea</hi> 14. 2. <hi>Take with you words, and turne to the Lord, ſay unto him, take away iniquity, and receive vs gratiouſly:</hi> They are the Saints <hi>practice, Ezra</hi> 9. 9. <hi>O Lord my God I am aſhamed, and bluſh to lift vp my face to to thee my God: for our iniquities are
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:155377:12"/> increaſed over our heads, and our treſpaſſe is growne vp vnto the Heavens: Dan.</hi> 9. 4, 5. <hi>I ſet my face vnto the Lord God, and to ſeeke by prayer and ſupplication, with faſting, and ſackcloth, and aſhes, and I prayed vnto the Lord my God and made my confeſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the explicating of this poynt, I will ſhew, firſt, wherein a true confeſſion of ſinne ſtands: Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, in what manner it muſt be performed.</p>
            <p>True confeſſion is made vp of two particulars, <hi>ſui ipſius accuſatio, ſui ipſius condemnatio:</hi> of a mans accuſing of himſelfe, and of a mans judging of himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Firſt, in accuſing himſelfe, he is to be <hi>coelestis et fidelis Dei orator contra ſeipſum,</hi> (as <hi>Pariſienſis</hi> ſpeakes) a heavenly and faithful pleader for God againſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: he is to ſet out his ſinnes with thoſe particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar aggravations, that have run into them, and doe truly greaten them in Gods ſight: for as in <hi>Greek,</hi> we doe not vſually pronounce according to to the long or ſhort Syllable, but accorditg to the <hi>Accent;</hi> ſo in ſinne, God doth not alwayes judg the greatnes from the Fact, but from the circumſtances with which it is committed: or as in matter of Grace, God doth not weigh it by the <hi>Scale,</hi> but tries it by the <hi>touch-ſtone;</hi> ſo in ſinne God doth not weigh it by the <hi>bulke,</hi> but by the <hi>ingreadients.</hi> A ſinne of a leſſer magnitude committed with <hi>light,</hi> with <hi>love,</hi> ſtirres vp and provokes God more, then a greater ſinne with reluctancy, paſſion, or ſurprizall: for <hi>gravius est pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum diligere, quam committere,</hi> it is far worſe to be in love with ſinne, then to commit it, as <hi>Gregorie</hi> well ſaith.</p>
            <p>Secondly, In condemning a mans ſelfe, he is to paſſe a ſevere Sentence againſt himſelf, by acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:155377:13"/> that God may juſtly let him ſinke in the middeſt of his rebellions, without caſting forth a new cord of mercie to help or ſave; thus did the humble <hi>Prodigall, Luke</hi> 15. 18. 19. <hi>I have ſinned againſt Heaven and before thee, and am no more worthy to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led thy Sonne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now in the doing of theſe there is a double good that the ſinner gets in the accuſing of himſelfe, he puts Sathan that is the great accuſer of the Brethren quite out of office, he can lay no more to his charge, then he hath already layed to his owne in condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning himſelfe; he puts God out of office (as I may ſo ſpeake) who will not judge them, that have judged and ſentenced themſelves, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 31.</p>
            <p>But to ſpeake more diſtinctly of this firſt part of confeſſion, <hi>viz,</hi> ſelfe accuſation; give me leave to propound three particulars about it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Three partic. in ſelfe accuſat.</note> Firſt the <hi>Inditement and charge, that a man prefers againſt himſelfe, it muſt be ſpeciall, and not generall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Confeſſion with many is reckoned to be well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough done, when that ſome few ſuch overlie ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions drop from their lips, as, that they are ſinners God help them, and who is not? and they are hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſorry for what they have done; but if you deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend to particulars, run over the whole Law, and they plead not guilty; Images they defie, ſweare they do not, and for Church they come with the firſt, and goe with the laſt, as for repentance, if you aske them wherin it lyes, they anſwer not much vnlike him in <hi>Quintilian,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Quintil. inſt. l. 2. c. 11.</note> who being demanded, what <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, what <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> was; replyed, truly he could not tell, but if it were any thing to the purpoſe, he was ſure it was in his Declamation: what repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and ſorrow for ſinne is, they cannot tell, but
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:155377:13"/> ſure they are, they have long agoe repented for their ſinnes. But how wide ſuch acknowledgments are from that exact confeſſion which the Scriptures call for, the practice of repenting ſinners doth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly evince. How often is <hi>David</hi> vpon his knees in confeſſing his murther, his adulterie? what an Hiſtorie doth <hi>Nehemiah</hi> make of Iſraels ſinnes in his prayer to God? <note place="margin">Neh. cap. 9.</note> how particularly doth <hi>Paul</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe his madneſſe againſt the Church, his blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies againſt Chriſt? and all to this end, that them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves may be more aſhamed, and God the more glorified. In ſinnes indeed of ignorance God is pleaſed to accept of confeſſion in the generall, and in the lumpe, but for ſinnes of knowledge he lookes that they be brought in as diſtinct debts, and vrged in our confeſſions as ſo many new Indite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments againſt our ſelves.</p>
            <p>Seconly, as we are to charge particulars vpon our ſelves, ſo alſo among them <hi>to ſingle and cull out our principall and cheife ſinnes, ſtreading them before God with all their aggravations:</hi> As Phiſitions in their <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomie Lectures,</hi> though the whole body lye before them, yet they read cheifely upon ſome more no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and Architectonical parts, the braine, the heart, the ſtomach, or the like, ſo in our humiliations, though we bring the whole body of ſinne and death into Gods preſence, yet are we to dwell andinſiſt cheiſly vpon thoſe corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, which have a greater tranſcendency of evill in them above o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: As for inſtance, vpon our vnbeleife, which is a mother ſinne, and carries a thouſand others in the wombe of of it: vpon your wordly minded<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which takes of the ſtrength of all our affections from God, and pitcheth it vpon the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:155377:14"/> creature, like to an ill ſpleene that robs the body of it's beſt noriſhment to feed it ſelfe. Vpon the breaking of our ſolemne Covenants made and renewed with God, a ſinne which above many others, hath helped to vnſheath the Sword of God againſt vs, and to let forth that diſpeaſure and indignation of the Lord, which burnes like a fire, that will not be quenched.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>In Confeſſion we are to charge vpon our ſelves thoſe powerfull ſtirrings of luſt, which ſpring from the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full frame and conſtitution of our nature</hi> and derive a venome to everie action that comes from us; ſin being in the facultie, as poyſon in the Fountaine, that ſheds infection into everie thing, that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedes from it. And this is it, which begets an indiſpoſition of heart to holy ſervices, that in our prayers damps our zeale, fervencie, humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, ſelfe abhorrency; that in our meditations makes vs roving and vnſetled, driving to no poynt or iſſue, like a ſhip in a tempeſt, that toſſes much, and ſayles little; that in our converſe mingles much levitie, frowardneſſe, vnfaithfullneſſe: in a word, that is it, which though it doe not make our ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly duties ſinnes, and ſo hatefull to God, (as our Adverſaries ſlander vs) <note place="margin">Bellarm. de juſtif. lib. 4. cap. 10.</note> yet doth contribute ſuch a vitiouſneſſe, as a foule channel doth to cleane water, to everie thing that proceeds from vs, as that God may juſtly charge vs for mixing our ſin with his grace, and throw all our beſt workes as dung in our faces. Great reaſon is there therefore, that we ſhould both accuſe our ſelves for this pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity and deordination of nature, and before God condemne and ſentence our ſelves for the curſed fruites that flow from it, which is the ſecond branch
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:155377:14"/> of true confeſſion, that is breifly to be vnfol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
            <p>This <hi>ſelfe condemnation lyeth in two things.</hi> Firſt in acknowledgment, that the vmoſt wrath and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of God is juſtly due to ſuch ſinnes as we have fallen into: for though a juſtified perſon by his tranſgreſſions doe not <hi>de facto</hi> become ſubject to the wrath and vengence of God, being a perſon privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged and exempted from the maledictions of the law, yet they doe <hi>de merito</hi> make ſuch a perſon lyable to death; for the covenant of grace doth not nullifie the merit of ſinne, but cauſeth that ſinne ſhall not actually condemne and exclude ſuch a perſon from ſalvation; So that a regenerate man when he hath ſinned againſt God, may truly ſay, as the Prodigal did, <hi>Luke</hi> 15. 18. <hi>I have ſinned againſt heaven, and before thee, and am no more worthy to be called thy Sonue.</hi> Yea, it is his duty in ſuch a manner to ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence the merit of his ſinnes, that he may the more abundantly admire the riches and fulneſſe of that grace, that hath delivered him from ſo heavie a curſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>In ſelfe condemning:</hi> we muſt confeſſe that the ſmart and chaſtiſements from God, which for ſinne at any time we lye vnder, are exceeding juſt and righteous. Hath God withdrawen from any of vs the light of his countenance becauſe of our ſinnes, and turned his ſmiles into frownes? hath he ſealed vp our lips, ſtraitned our ſpirit? hath he kindled a fire in our bones, hath he blaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our eſtate, hath he put gall into our contentments, and made life it ſelfe a ſore and heavie burthen vnto vs? yet muſt we give glory vnto god, and ſay, as the Church did in the height of all it's afflictions,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:155377:15"/> 
               <hi>the Lord our God is righteous in all his workes; for we have not obeyed his veyce, Dan.</hi> 9. 14,</p>
            <p>I come now to the manner, how the duty of confeſſion is to be performed, and that conſiſts of of divers ingredients and qulifications.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Five Qualific. in a true Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion.</note> Firſt, <hi>a genuine confeſſion of ſinne muſt be performed, with a great meaſure of ſelfe abaſing, and ſelfe humbling.</hi> The Leaper in the Law <hi>Lev.</hi> 13. 45. was preſcribed to have ſuch a carriage and behaviour, as might moſt clearely expreſſe his ſhame and ſorrow for ſuch ſins as had drawn ſo heavy hand of God vpon him, he was to goe with his garments rent, that all might ſee and behold his leaproſie: with his head bare, to typiſie what a ſervant of ſervants he had been what a drudge to his luſts, and the will of the fleſh: with his lip covered, to expreſſe (as ſome of the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes ſay,) that he was fit for no companie or friendly ſalutes, but to ſit and mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e alone: to crie, vncleane, vncleane; thereby to proclaime his owne miſerie, and forwarne others that they approach him not, leaſt they be defiled by touching him: this deportment of the Leaper, ſome of the Antients have thought, to be a lively embleme of a penitent and broken ſinner, who when he come before God, to acknowledge his vileneſſe, is to vſe all meanes, and to take all advantages of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſing and ſhaming himſelf in his preſence: <note place="margin">Vide Mendoc. in lib. 1. Reg. cap. 7. Num. 6. Annot. 25.</note> he is in ſome meaſure to afflict his body in the laying a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide all ornaments; he is to confeſſe his vaſſalage to his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in whoſe ſervice his hands and his heart have bin ſo much hardned: he is to mourne, as one that deſerves to have none to be a comforter: he is with doubled and loud confeſſions to crie
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:155377:15"/> out before God and man, that he is <hi>as an vncleane thing, and all his righteouſneſſes are as filthy ragges, Iſaiah</hi> 64. 6.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>true confeſſion as it debaſeth a ſinner, ſo muſt it exalt and ſet vp God.</hi> In this worke God and a ſinner are like unto <hi>quantitas diſcreta,</hi> and quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titas <hi>continua,</hi> the one of which may be infinitely diminiſhed, and the other infinitely increaſed: Gods mercy in bearing, pardoning, healing that may be highned, and exalted without bounds, and man, wretchedneſſe and baſeneſſe that may be ſo aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated, as to make him worſe then nothing: Both theſe things doth <hi>Nehemiah</hi> excellently performe, in that confeſſion which he makes in the behalfe of the Church, which is all interchangeably woven and interſtreaked with an holy exalting of Gods goodneſſe, and a ſerious acknowledgment of their vileneſſe. He begins <hi>cap.</hi> 9. <hi>ver.</hi> 7. to <hi>ver.</hi> 16. with a pithie and ſweet abridgment of Gods goodnes to Iſrael, made knowne in eminent deliverances, pretious mercies, and ſtrange miracles: then he ſubjoynes their ill requitall of this his love, from <hi>ver.</hi> 16. to <hi>ver.</hi> 19. then from <hi>ver.</hi> 19. <hi>to ver.</hi> 26. he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares a new, how good God was to them, when they had been thus evill to him: and then againe addes, their inflexableneſſe and diſobedience vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all his continued goodneſſe. And thus like checker worke in white and blacke, in a narration of Gods mercies, and Iſraels vnthankefulneſſe, he continues his prayer vnto the end.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, a <hi>true Confeſſion muſt be voluntarie. Pij non trahuntur ad tribunal dei, ſed ſponte accedunt:</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men prevent ſummons in Gods Court, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:155377:16"/> vp on a voluntarie appearance, they are active in this worke, and not paſſive. Wicked men when God awakens their conſciences in their boſome, and makes the ſmell of the brimſtone and the fire of Hell, to come up into their noſtrils, when their ſoule is ſitting upon their lips, and ready to take it's flight into an other world, will then happily crie out of their ſinnes, and ſeeke pardon, which in their lives they have diſpiſed; but all this is like the howling devotion of ſome, deſperate mariner in a ſtorme, which is not at all out of aflection, but out of feare, which will in the end be as farre from peace, as it is at the preſent from trueth, it is the volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie penitent that finds mercie, and not he <hi>qui ad delinquendum exporrigit frontem, ad confitendum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trahit,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Tertul.</note> 
               <hi>as</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>a true confeſſion it muſt be reall and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It muſt be a worke of the heart, and not of the lips, elſe though we be much in the dutie, we ſhall reape litle of the fruite of it. Sinceritie is that, which in everie ſervice obtaines the bleſſing, but eſpeciall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in this, when an humbled ſoule lies in the middeſt of darkeneſſe as in a dungeon, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceritie in it's prayers in it's confeſſions, is as a chinke to let in ſome beames of light, and hope, when as all ſhewes and pretenſes without it in any kind whatſoever, are but like windowes faſtned vpon a thicke wall, that though they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute beautie to the building, and ſeeme ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious to the beholder without, doe yet tranſmit no light to the dweller within.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:155377:16"/>
            <p>Fiftly, <hi>a true confeſſion muſt exclude a willing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to ſinne againe.</hi> Among many names which <hi>Pariſienſes</hi> gives to confeſion, this is one, he cals it <hi>ſpiritualis vomitus,</hi> ſpirituall vomit, whereby the burthened ſoul doth eaſe it ſelfe, like an overchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged ſtomake by getting vp that, which lies hard and indigeſted upon it. Now it is the part of a dogge to take up his vomit, and not of a man, much leſſe of a chriſtian.</p>
            <p>Oh therefore take heed what you doe, that are exerciſed in the weighty duties of this Day! doe not turne your faſtings and confeſſions into a lye by to morrowes looſe living, contradict not the words that have gon forth out of your mouthes, by a freſh practice of ſuch ſinnes, which you have now engaged your ſelves to relinquiſh, let no luſt that you have profeſſed this day to be a thorne in your ſides, be as a crowne or garland on your head to morrow, take nothing againe as a freind into your boſome, that you have this day looked upon as an enemie, But if any man ſhall dare to mocke God, and by freſh apoſtacies to breake the ſolemne covennat that he hath now entered into, let him know this for a certaine, that if there be juſtice in Heaven, or fire in Hell, he ſhall one day be filled with the bitter fruits of his owne wayes, and ſhall find the wages of ſinne to be death. For the application of this poynt, I ſhall confine my ſelfe unto two Vſes, the firſt whereof ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt only of ſome directions, that may help us in confeſſion, which to performe aright, is not the leaſt part of a chriſtians worke or care.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. Vſe.</note> Firſt, <hi>ſtudie well your hearts.</hi> the heart is a vaſt maze
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:155377:17"/> and labyrinth, in which not he that runnes faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, ſooneſt comes to an end, but he that walkes moſt circumſpectly: as a darke vault, that ſtands in need of al the candles of the Lord, for to enlighten it: as a vaſt Sea, which needs the longeſt line for to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thome it: and the more you are acquainted with it, the more you ſhall ſee cauſe to abhorre your-ſelves, and matter to plead againſt your-ſelves. There are in the eye a thouſand vanities, adulteries, pride, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſitie, thefts, and the like, but <hi>ſi trabs in oculo, ſylva in corde,</hi> if there be a beame in the eye, there is a wood in the heart: there are in the hands violence, rapines, bloudſhed, but they are there only as water in a ſtream, the heart is the fountaine, that feeds and nouriſheth it: in all the members there is a fulneſſe of ſin, but the heart is the roote that derives life and ſtrength vnto all: as the Sea, that filles the Rivers, but yet it ſelfe is never the leſſe emptie: After all communications and diffuſions of luſt into everie fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie there are in the heart as the proper ſeate, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſme, blaſphemies, treaſons againſt the very life and being of God, ſins at which the very fleſh itſelfe will quake and tremble, when they doe begin to peep and put out in the verie ſhaddow of a thought.</p>
            <p>Now can a man that is any way apprehenſive, that he hath ſuch a treaſure, ſuch an Hell, ſuch a maga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin of ſins within him, want what to confeſſe? and what to condemne himſelfe for in the ſight of God? no certanly, words he may want, and teares and ſighes, but never matter of confeſſion, and aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, were his life drawne out to an eternitie. it is the ignorance only that men have of their hearts, that filles them with pride, boaſtings, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptions
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:155377:17"/> of their eſtates, opinions of their good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that make them like the Phariſie that can find little to confeſſe, but much to commend him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe for; whereas if God did but diſcover the true condition of their hearts vnto them, they would like the Publican knock and ſmite their breſts? and cry out, Lord be mercifull to me a ſinner.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Get a ſpirituall knowledge of the Law of God.</hi> That is it which as a light diſcovers thoſe corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and ſins which lie hid and vnſeen in the darke night of ignorance, and makes them to appeare in their due ſhape and proportion: <hi>Paul</hi> while this light of the Law ſhone into his heart, was <hi>alive</hi> (as himſelfe confeſſeth) <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 9. full of conceits of his own righteouſneſſe, and abilities to performe what ever the Law had required to ſalvation: but when <hi>the Commandement came, ſinne revived, and Paul dyed:</hi> all his preſumptions and miſperſwations they withered and fell away as leaves doe from the trees in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumne, and his ſins they like the Crowes neſts ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, which before are unſeen and undiſcerned: then he ſaw that to be a mountaine, which before he judged to be a moate, and that to be ſin, which before he looked vpon as righteouſneſſe, then he ſaw much to bemoan, much to confeſſe, and to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed of, but nothing to boaſt, and glorie of: ſome ſins indeed the weake glimmerings of nature may diſcover vnto men to be vile; lying, luxurie, idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; the <hi>Cretian Poet</hi> could tax in his owne countrie men: but to read over the whole Hiſtorie of a mans life without any other candle, is as impoſſible, as to turne over great volumes by the light of a glow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worme.<note place="margin">Tit. 1. 12.</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:155377:18"/>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Keepe alive in your hearts, the apprehenſion, of ſome particular ſinnes, for which God hath deeply humbled you.</hi> Chriſtians in their way to Heaven as thay are not without aſſaults, temptations, importunities of the fleſh; So are they not ſometimes without fals and bruſes, luſts tempt and they yeild, the fleſh flatters and muſt be gratified, and by this meanes oftentimes their peace is impaired, and their conſciences deeply wounded: Now if any of us have ſuch blacke dayes in our Calenders, ſuch foule ſins in our private Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſters, that may mind us what we have ſometimes bin, let vs as much as we can, keep vp the apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of that deformitie, uglineſſe, contrariety to the Law, which they ſeemed to have, when firſt God ſet them vpon our conſciences, the freſh remembrance of ſin in this kind; it is like a peaſe in an iſſue, that keeps it open and makes it run: it makes the heart to be in a broaken and melting frame, to be free in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion and earneſt in prayer, that God would ſhew him mercy, and let him live before him.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>Reflect ſeriouſly vpon your wayes.</hi> Running waters caſt no ſhaddow, no more doe fleeting thougts make any repreſentation of a mans condition: he that rides poſt, can never make a true mappe of a Countrie, nor that man any diſcoverie of himſelfe whoſe thoughts doe not now and then make a ſtand and looke backward, it is conſideration, that tels vs what need we ſtand in of mercie to pardon us, and what need we have to confeſſe our ſinnes, that we may be pardoned: it's conſideration, that makes the iſſues of ſinne dreadfull, and cauſeth us with trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling to ſeeke him whom we have offended, and to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urne our feete unto his Teſtimonies.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:155377:18"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. Vſe.</note> A ſecond Vſe is in breife to diſcover. how injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous they are, not only vnto themſelves, but unto the the happineſſe of the whole Kingdome, that would in theſe ſad times crie downe all acknowledgment and confeſſion of ſinne, as that which is vſeleſſe, and unbecomming the dayes and times of the Goſpel, and would by certaine artes and wyles put a beautie vpon moſt miſhapen and deformed opinions. <hi>Pauſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nias</hi> tels a ſtorie, of a mirrour in the Temple of <hi>Smyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> that if any that had a beautifull face, looked in it, he would appeare exceedingly deformed; and if any that were ilfavoured did looke in it, they did appeare beautifull and amiable. not much unlike to this glaſſe are their fancies, which render the bleſſed truthes of God, ſorrow for ſinne, confeſſion of ſinne, and prayer for pardon, as things that the Law of the Goſpel doth not injoyne, or Chriſt accept, and crie up a libertie and freedom from the Law, as a rule to guide and order our converſations, by which Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion if they ſhould once come to prevaile in mens minds, they will quickely bid farwell to all holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. But I ſpare to ſpeake any more, becauſe that you with whom the weightie affaires of the Church are betruſted, will doe that right to the Goſpel and trueth, which ſhall beſeeme Perſons of your worth and pietie.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Page 13. l. 4. for devotious r. directions. pag. 14. l. 8. r. pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, pag. 17. l. 10. r. ſtroak.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:155377:19"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Die Jovis 27. Julij, 1643.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is this day Ordered by the Lords in Parliament, that Maſter <hi>Spurſtowe</hi> hath hereby thankes given him from their Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, for the great paines taken by him in his Sermon he made in Saint <hi>Margarets</hi> Church <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> before the Lords and Commons on Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day the 21. of this inſtant <hi>July,</hi> at the publike Humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation; And is hereby deſired to cauſe his ſaid Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to be forthwith Printed and Publiſhed.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>John Browne Cler. Parl.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Die Veneris 21. Julij, 1643.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is this day Ordered by the Houſe of Commons, that Maſter <hi>Salloway</hi> doe give thankes to Maſter <hi>Spurſtowe,</hi> who at the deſire of the Houſe this day Preached be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Commons at St. <hi>Margarets, Weſtminſter,</hi> it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an extraordinary day of publicke Humiliation, and that he be deſired to print his Sermon. And it is Ordered that no man ſhall print his Sermon, but whom the ſaid Mr. <hi>Spurſtowe</hi> ſhall Authorize under his hand-writing.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H. Elſygne Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="appointment">
            <p>I appoint <hi>Peter Cole</hi> to print my Sermon.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>William Spurſtowe</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
